Joshua Nelson

Software Engineer

joshcdnelson@gmail.com • 9715703991 • Church Hill, TN

Profile

Experienced software engineer blends a background in engineering and marketing leadership to consistently deliver new product features and APIs emphasizing performance, long-term maintainability, and organizational goals. Leverages a strong technical foundation and inventiveness to develop customized solutions for complex problem domains.

Professional Experience

05/2020 - present

Software Engineer, KollaCode

Remote

- Rearchitected an interactive ETL application that handles 100,000 records at a time, utilized web workers and asynchronous best practices to offload computationally intensive operations, resulting in a 15-second reduction between processing steps
- Built browser and desktop application featuring online-offline syncing capability written using Node, React, and Electron, with an IndexedDB database

12/2018 - 03/2020

Software Engineer, Opal

Portland, OR

- Full-stack engineer on a monolithic application written in Ruby on Rails, Node, and Typescript React with Redux, with a PostgreSQL database
- Implemented and extended JSON:API-compliant Rail's endpoints, moving existing business logic into maintainable, conventional patterns
- Built data-intensive views in React as well as refactored application-wide filtering architecture, eliminating several longstanding bugs and component architectural inconsistencies
- Created internal design system, enforcing consistent visual design and adhering to WCAG 2.1

05/2018 - 11/2018

Software Engineer, PlinkoJS (www.plinkojs.com)

Remote

- Co-created an open-source, multiplayer, real-time, browser-based physics game using Node, React, and WebSockets
- Featured a client-server architecture to synchronize game state, generated by a physics engine, to four clients in real-time, while facilitating live-action gameplay
- Researched game state synchronization models and determined the best fit based on the tradeoffs each model had on gameplay and network architecture
- Implemented strategies around binary data serialization and compression, latency estimation, client-side prediction, network protocols, and snapshot buffering and interpolation to simulate a lag-free, real-time user experience
- PlinkoJS White Paper: http://plinkojs.com/about

09/2016 - 04/2018

Manager, Marketing and Business Development Strategy,

Albany, OR

Linn-Benton Community College

- Brought in software solutions that saved the department \$20,000 in annual expenses
- Built websites for unique program offerings, increasing accessibility of services

Education

2008 - 2012

B.Sc. Marketing, Management Leadership, Portland State University